Guide to the Delta Kappa Gamma Society, Eta Chapter (Missoula, Montana) Records 1944-1996
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Delta Kappa Gamma Society, Eta Chapter (Missoula, Montana) Records
1944-1996
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 601
Delta Kappa Gamma Society, Eta Chapter (Missoula, Montana)
4.5 linear feet
The collection contains minutes of meetings, membership information, yearbooks, financial records, photographs, writings, scrapbooks, and materials from projects undertaken by the Eta Chapter of Delta Kappa Gamma Society, including the restoration of the Hellgate Trading Post and the Grant Creek One-Room Schoolhouse now at Fort Missoula.
Historical Note
Delta Kappa Gamma Sorority International is an honorary society for women educators. The Eta Chapter was organized on May 6, 1944, in Missoula, Montana, at the Florence Hotel. Since its inception, the chapter raised money to fund a wide range of projects, including scholarships for members to seek further professional education and charitable causes in their community. The members formed a committee to restore the Hellgate Trading Post, beginning in 1950. The property was later sold to the Hillstroms, who worked with Eta Chapter to preserve the site. By 1976, the Grant Creek Schoolhouse at Fort Missoula became the chapter’s restoration project. They restored and furnished the schoolhouse building and published a history of the school in 1981, written by Mildred Dufresne. The schoolhouse was dedicated that same year.
As of 2004 the organization was still active.
The collection contains minutes of meetings, membership information, yearbooks, financial records, photographs, scrapbooks, and materials from projects undertaken by the Eta Chapter of Delta Kappa Gamma Society, including the restoration of the Hellgate Trading Post and the Grant Creek One-Room Schoolhouse now at Fort Missoula. The scrapbooks contain photographs, programs, clippings, and other memorabilia, from 1944 to 1996. The collection contains writings prepared by its members about women in education, the Grant Creek project, the history of public high school education in Missoula, and chapter histories. There are also some copies of the state’s Delta Kappa Gamma Society newsletter, Alphamusings.
The collection contains a small portion of materials from Alpha Mu and other Montana chapters, including yearbooks and other writings.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
Gifts of Delta Kappa Gamma, Eta Chapter, in 1991 and Marilyn Denny in 2000
Delta Kappa Gamma Society national publications, including newsletters and publications, were removed from the collection during processing.
The records of the Alpha Mu Chapter of Delta Kappa Gamma Society are at the Museum of Women’s History in Billings, Montana.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Grant Creek School.; Delta Kappa Gamma Society. Eta Chapter (Missoula, Mont.)
Hellgate Trading Post; Missoula (Mont.)--Buildings, structures, etc.
Charities--Montana -- Missoula; Greek letter societies -- Montana--Missoula; Historic buildings -- Conservation and restoration--Montana--Missoula; Scholarships--Montana -- Missoula; Women--Montana -- Missoula--Societies and clubs; Women educators--Montana --Missoula--Societies, etc.; Women in charitable work -- Montana--Missoula
Women; Missoula
- Minutes, 1944-1953 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Minutes, 1953-1962 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Minutes, 1967-1978 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Minutes, 1978-1984 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Yearbooks, 1952-1960 (Box-folder 1/5)
- Yearbooks, 1960-1975 (Box-folder 2/1)
- Yearbooks, 1975-1990 (Box-folder 2/2)
- Gamma Chapter Yearbooks, 1960-1963 (Box-folder 2/3)
- Alpha Mu Chapter Yearbooks and Reference Outlines, 1981-1986 and undated (Box-folder 2/4)
- Membership, 1944-1976 (Box-folder 2/5)
- Membership, 1961-1986 (Box-folder 2/6)
- Member deaths, 1966-1978 and undated (Box-folder 2/7)
- Transfers and resignees, 1944-1980 (Box-folder 3/1)
- President’s Reports and Committee Reports, 1950-1978 (Box-folder 3/2)
- Committee on Program, 1958-1984 (Box-folder 3/3)
- Scholarship material both for Eta and Alpha Mu Chapters, 1968-1983 and undated (Box-folder 3/4)
- Delta Kappa Gamma Society, manuals, 1961-1968 and undated (Box-folder 3/5)
- State reports, Personal Growth and Services Committee, Regional Workshops, 1979 (Box-folder 3/6)
- Chapter President, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 3/7)
- Founders Day Ceremony, 1979-1984 (Box-folder 3/8)
- Parliamentary Procedure, 1979-1985 and undated (Box-folder 3/9)
- Communications Guide, 1981 (Box-folder 3/10)
- Conventions, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 3/11)
- Delta Kappa Gamma Society, Alpha Mu Chapter Directories, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 3/12)
- Miscellaneous, 1965-1989 and undated (Box-folder 4/1)
- Montana chapter histories, circa 1945 and undated (Box-folder 4/2)
- "Then Came the Teacher: Pioneer Women Teachers," Alpha Mu State, (1959-1961) (Box-folder 4/3)
- "Alpha Mu Pays Tribute To Those Who Served," publication, 1963-1985 (Box-folder 4/4)
- "Public High School Education in Missoula, 1884-1955" by Agnes Brown, 1970 (Box-folder 4/5)
- "Our Golden Anniversary: Delta Kappa Gamma: 1929-1979" (Box-folder 5/1)
- "Jennie: Collection of Writings by Jennie Tvaruzek", circa 1989 (Box-folder 5/2)
- "Eta Chapter History-Alpha Mu State, Delta Kappa Gamma Society International, 1944-1989," 1990 (Box-folder 5/3)
- Carolyn Frojen, research, 1974-1982 (Box-folder 5/4)
- Hillstorm Ranch, Hellgate Restoration Project, 1957-1962 (Box-folder 5/5)
- "Forty Years of Dreams Come True-Grant Creek School House", 1981 (Box-folder 5/6)
- Grant Creek and its One-Room School by Mildred Dufresne, circa 1981 (Box-folder 5/7)
- Grant Creek School, 1981 and undated (Box-folder 5/8)
- Grant Creek School, 1981 and undated (Box-folder 5/9)
- Grant Creek School, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 5/10)
- Member photographs, circa 1970s-1980s (Box-folder 5/11)
- Activities-Homecoming, etc., slides, undated (Box-folder 5/12)
- Photographs and negatives, undated (Box-folder 5/13)
- Delta Kappa Gamma Bulletin, 1939 (Box-folder 6/1)
- Delta Kappa Gamma Society, manuals, 1971-1982 (Box-folder 6/2)
- Alphamusings, 1949-1971 (Box-folder 6/3)
- Alphamusings, 1972-1987 (Box-folder 6/4)
- Treasurer’s book, 1944-1964 (Box-folder 6/5)
- Treasurer’s book, 1964-1971 (Box-folder 6/6)
- Treasurer’s book, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 6/7)
- Treasurer’s book, 1975-1981 (Box-folder 7/1)
- Membership dues, 1946-1980 (Box-folder 7/2)
- Annual Report of Chapter Treasurer, 1950-1982 (Box-folder 7/3)
- Income tax, 1965-1973 (Box-folder 7/4)
- Treasurer correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 7/5)
- Transfers, 1971-1977 (Box-folder 7/6)
- Board of Directors-Clarice Willsey, 1971-1981 and undated (Box-folder 7/7)
- Bills and receipts, 1972-1977 (Box-folder 7/8)
- Treasurer correspondence, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 7/9)
- Treasurer information, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 7/10)
- Hellgate fund, undated (Box-folder 7/11)
- Hand-made Delta Kappa Gamma felt crest [used in a ceremony, from Helene Longan], undated (Box OS 8)
- Scrapbook, 1944-1977 (Box OS 9)
- Scrapbook, 1970-1980 (Box OS 9)
- Scrapbook, 1953-1970 (Box OS 10)
- Charter, 1944 (Box OS 11)
- Scrapbook, 1987-1996 (Box OS 11)